Guide to the Thönges Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thönges family papers
1862-1903
1862-1880
MS 489
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist almost entirely of correspondence between Heinrich Thönges in Steinfurth, Germany and his children in the United States. Included are descriptions of life during the Civil War and addresses to commemorate the Battle of Antietam.
Thönges family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert C. Meyer.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists, except for a few items, of letters of various members of the Thönges Family. The most representative is Heinrich Thönges, the father, who writes from Steinfurth, Germany to his children resident in the United states. The rest of the mterial consists of letters from the various children and brothers of Heinrich.
The letters from Heinrich contain advice consistent with his Protestant ethic, while the children's letters have fleeting glimpses of life during the U. S. Civil War in which they participated. Those of the father contain mostly platitudes and on the whole rather useless advice to children who are offering their lives in the Civil War. A commendably strong faith in God tends, unfortunately, to blur any pragramtic considerations, which might be of some profit to the children. On the whole the letters are fairly interesting reading, but it is doubtful that they are of great historical significance.
The collection is entirely in Geman except for the letter of Chester K. knight (1863 Nov 29) and the reply thereto from Conrad Thönges (1864 Jan 24).
Antietam, Battle of, Md., 1862; Families; Germans -- United States; Europe; Germany; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Thönges family
- Original accession
  - Thönges, Peter ALS to Conrad Thönges, Louisville, KY, 1862 October 8 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Louis ALS to Conrad Thönges, Cincinatti, OH, 1862 October 25 (Box 1)
  - Philippi, Louis ALS to Contad Thönges, Crawford Co., IL, 1863 March 1 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Contad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1863 March 8 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Contad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1863 March 22 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Peter ALS to unknown, Winchester, TN, 1863 August 10 (Box 1)
  - Knight, Chester K. ALS to Conrad Thönges, Bridgeport, AL, 1863 November 29 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Conrad ALS to Chester K. Knight, New York City, 1864 January 24 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1864 April 10 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Philip ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1864 May 10 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1864 October 9 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1865 October 8 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1866 June 17 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1866 November 20 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1867 July 1 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1869 February 20 (Box 1)
  - Two leaves of notes unknown person, New York City, 1870 February 20 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Eberhard ALS to Louis Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1870 December 26 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1871 March 5 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1871 July 1 (Box 1)
  - Hessenbliker, Wilhelm ALS to Conrad Thönges, Ternton, NJ, 1871 July 23 (Box 1)
  - Philippi, Lewis ALS to Conrad Thönges, Majority Point, IL, 1872 February 4 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1873 June 29 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Ludwig ALS to unknown person, San Francisco,CA, 1875 October 27 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1876 February 21 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1876 July 12 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1878 September 20 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Conrad ALS to unknown person, New York City, 1880 July 31 (Box 1)
  - Draft of an address to commemorate the battle of Antietam, 1882 September 17 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1889 March 17 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1889 October 18 (Box 1)
  - Antietam. An unsigned address to "Kamareden, Freunde and vershrte Damen.", 1891 September 17 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to Conrad Thönges, Steinfurth, Germany, 1903 April 1 (Box 1)
  - Thönges, Heinrich ALS to unknown person, undated (Box 1)
  - Schulte, Eduard: peom entitled "Arm und Reich", undated (Box 1)
  - Fragment of draft of letter. Unsigned, New York, undated (Box 1)
  - Two drafts of an address to "Friends of the athletic Society and Comrades", undated (Box 1)